This is the Mono cabab, a two- wheeled
gyroscopic, autonomous, batterypowered
rail pod balancing itself on a single
rail. According to its creators, the
Mono cabab is a high-tech, flexible,
individualized mode of sustainable rail
transportation that can breathe new life
into closed down branch lines. Do you
live near one of those branch lines and
want to travel somewhere? Just open the
app and order one of the rail pods, and
they will whisk you to your destination
in a cabin slightly wider than a coffin.
All while balancing itself on a single
rail using their built-in gyroscopes.
Why on a single rail? Indeed, why? So
that two pots can pass each other even
on a single track, bringing much needed
capacity to these deserted branch lines
no one uses. Okay, so why is this idea
the height of idiocy and what should we
build instead? Let's take a look. The
Mono cab is marketing itself basically
as an Uber on rails. Just go to your
local closed down branch line, open the
app, call a train, I'm sorry, a pod, and
then wait half an hour until your
painfully slow rolling coffin shows up
to you. And this whole idea is a result
of two major failures. One on a systemic
level and one on an individual level.
We'll talk about the systemic failure in
a moment. As far as the individual level
is concerned, it is extremely clear to
me that the people who came up with the
moto cab have absolutely no idea how
public transit works and least of all
how trains work. Look, these are trains.
These are also trains. Plush trains. My
plush trains, which are on sale now for
a limited time only. Get your own
American GG1 or Hungarian V63 locomotive
plushies now for just $29.99. You can
also get matching passenger cars for
each locomotive for only $18.99. You can
use them as ornaments, pillows, or tools
to discipline your pets.
[Music]
And of course, you support the channel
with each purchase. To get the plushies,
go to plushyo.com/collections/adam
something, which you will also find in
the description. Thank you for your kind
attention.
[Music]
Okay, so the monocap, as painfully
stupid this whole thing is, the
underlying idea is quite noble. You want
to find a way to restore rail service on
abandoned branch lines. And you want to
do that because trains are a great form
of transportation. They are efficient,
scalable, fast, high capacity, and the
technology needed to create a
functioning service can be very simple.
For example, Switzerland's first
electrified line was inaugurated in
1899. We know how to build efficient,
high-capacity, environmentally friendly
rail. We've been doing it for one and a
quarter centuries, but then tech bros
are like, "Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's cool
and all. Epic 420, Marvel, all that. But
what if we took such a system and made
it worse in pretty much every way?" Why?
Because it needs to travel on a single
rail so that two trains, I'm sorry, pods
can pass each other. So you can operate
a single track line as a double track
line at the low low price of forcing
passengers into mobile coffins. But why
do you need the flexibility and capacity
of a double track line on these low
traffic single track branch lines?
Because they're tech bros, that's why.
By that I mean they can only imagine the
system as an individualized one. You
don't have schedules. You have an app
because of course you do and you call a
train with the app because of course you
do and travel to your destination very
slowly in a battery powered autonomous
pod because of course you do. So how
about we try to improve this system
together? See if we can solve the many
issues plaguing it. First off we need to
get rid of the individualized mass
transit concept. What if we had this
thing called a schedule? Meaning that
vehicles will run at predetermined times
enabling us to plan ahead so that two
trains will never meet each other on a
single track section. Great. So now the
trains can have at least four wheels and
can therefore use both rails. So we can
get rid of all those moving parts in the
form of a goddamn spinning gyroscope
right under the passenger compartment.
Also we can now make the train cars
wider than a coffin. So you know kind of
like a regular [__] train. So there
we go. We solved the problem. Let's just
build a train, right? Well,
unfortunately that's not happening due
to the affforementioned systemic failure
when it comes to these projects. So this
whole Monocab line would operate between
the German city of Cleave and the Dutch
city of Negan. The Monoab is an attempt
to link two cities across the border
with transit. Currently your only option
is to take a bus which takes almost an
hour compared to driving which takes 23
minutes. So the Monocab wants to use the
former rail line between these two
cities to connect them once again. Both
Cla and Nagen have an active rail
connection, but the link between them is
missing. On the German side, it's
interrupted by a parking lot right after
Claver station. And in Neagen, the old
line converges with the existing double
track mainline, but is abandoned
completely. And this is the big systemic
issue. Our political leaders would
rather waste taxpayers money on some
[__] autonomous batterypowered appc
controlled gyroscopic tech coffin rather
than to invest money into real transit
like restoring the claim rail line by
electrifying it and running a fast
convenient rail service that could
compete with individual motor traffic.
However, there is a plot twist. The
German regional government is actually
very interested in restoring the rail
line. So are the locals in Clay which is
the German side. The problem is with the
Dutch side where residents of one town
growback do not want to hear it. They
don't want any trains running there
because the city already got built out
around the tracks and it would disturb
the French flare of the town's new
central area which is especially
frustrating since right after GB there
is the existing Dutch mainline to which
the line from Clayback could connect
thereby restoring the link to Neagan.
Gbeck is the only Dutch town on this
rail line and it's blocking the entire
project. So when it comes to the Mo cab
tech bros are the least of our worries.
The sorry state of transit here is first
off due to the 1990s neoliberal mania of
closing local rail lines, misguided
allocation of public grants and local
nimiism. But the situation is not
hopeless. I can definitely see some sort
of trimm train service that could
appease the nimbies and still provide
reasonable speed and quality. Tram
trains are well what the name says.
Inside cities they act like trams.
Outside cities they act like trains. The
city link is a great example. It's
basically a heavyduty tram capable of a
100 km/h top speed on regular heavy rail
tracks. So if you want to restore
service between Clay and Negan, do not
look to Montreal gyroscopic
batterypowered appc controlled coffin
pods. Just build a [__] tram train or
get a regular train in plush version.
You can go to Grossback and keep hitting
the nies with them until they change
their mind. Building or restoring a
transit line between cities is
difficult. It's a pain in the ass and
it's very much needed. But as always,
tech bros and their fever dreams will
not get us out of this mess. Time,
money, hard negotiations, and creativity
will, like the affforementioned TM train
solution. Thank you for watching, and
don't forget the plushies are available
for a limited time only. So, if you want
to get your hands on them, you can do it
now via this link, which you can also
find in the description. With that, I'll
be seeing you next time.